<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>

<rfc number="7999" category="info" submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">
    <front>


        <title abbrev="BLACKHOLE Community">BLACKHOLE Community</title>

        <author fullname="Thomas King" initials="T." surname="King">
            <organization abbrev='DE-CIX'>DE-CIX Management GmbH</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Lichtstrasse 43i</street>
                    <city>Cologne</city>
                    <code>50825</code>
                    <country>Germany</country>
                </postal>
                <email>thomas.king@de-cix.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Christoph Dietzel" initials="C." surname="Dietzel">
            <organization abbrev='DE-CIX'>DE-CIX Management GmbH</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Lichtstrasse 43i</street>
                    <city>Cologne</city>
                    <code>50825</code>
                    <country>Germany</country>
                </postal>
                <email>christoph.dietzel@de-cix.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Job Snijders" initials="J." surname="Snijders">
            <organization abbrev="NTT">NTT Communications</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Theodorus Majofskistraat 100</street>
                    <code>1065 SZ</code>
                    <city>Amsterdam</city>
                    <country>The Netherlands</country>
                </postal>
                <email>job@ntt.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>
        <author fullname="Gert Doering" initials="G." surname="Doering">
            <organization>SpaceNet AG</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>Joseph-Dollinger-Bogen 14</street>
                    <city>Munich</city>
                    <code>80807</code>
                    <country>Germany</country>
                </postal>
                <email>gert@space.net</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <author fullname="Greg Hankins" initials="G." surname="Hankins">
            <organization>Nokia</organization>
            <address>
                <postal>
                    <street>777 E. Middlefield Road</street>
                    <city>Mountain View</city>
                    <region>CA</region>
                    <code>94043</code>
                    <country>United States of America</country>
                </postal>
                <email>greg.hankins@nokia.com</email>
            </address>
        </author>

        <date month="October" year="2016" />

        <abstract>


            <t>
                This document describes the use of a well-known Border
                Gateway Protocol (BGP) community for destination-based
                blackholing in IP networks. This well-known advisory
		transitive BGP community named "BLACKHOLE" allows an origin
                Autonomous System (AS) to specify that a neighboring network should discard
                any traffic destined towards the tagged IP prefix.
            </t>
        </abstract>


    </front>

    <middle>
        <section anchor="intro" title="Introduction">
            <t>
                Network infrastructures have been increasingly hampered
                by DDoS attacks. In order to dampen the effects of these
                DDoS attacks, IP networks have offered blackholing with
                <xref target="RFC4271">BGP</xref> using various mechanisms
                such as those described in <xref target="RFC3882"/> and
                <xref target="RFC5635"/>.
            </t>

            <t>
                DDoS attacks targeting a certain IP address may cause
                congestion of links used to connect to adjacent networks. In order
                to limit the impact of such a scenario on legitimate traffic,
                networks adopted a mechanism called "BGP blackholing". A network
                that wants to trigger blackholing needs to understand the
                triggering mechanism adopted by its neighboring networks.
  Different networks provide different
  mechanisms to trigger blackholing, including but not limited to pre-
  defined blackhole next-hop IP addresses, specific BGP communities, or
  out-of-band BGP sessions with a special BGP speaker.
            </t>

            <t>
                Having several different mechanisms to trigger blackholing in
                different networks makes it an unnecessarily complex,
                error-prone, and cumbersome task for network operators.
                Therefore, a well-known <xref target="RFC1997">BGP
                    community</xref> is defined for operational ease.
            </t>

            <t>
                Having such a well-known BGP community for blackholing also
                further simplifies network operations because:
                <list style='symbols'>
                    <t>Implementing and monitoring blackholing becomes easier
                        when implementation and operational guides do not cover
                        many variations to trigger blackholing.
                    </t>
                    <t>The number of support requests from customers about how
                        to trigger blackholing in a particular neighboring
                        network will be reduced as the codepoint for common
                        blackholing mechanisms is unified and well-known.
                    </t>
                </list>
            </t>

        <section title="Requirements Language">

            <t>
                The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
                "SHALL NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED",
                "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" are to be interpreted as described
                in <xref target="RFC2119"/> only when they appear in all
                upper case. They may also appear in lower case or mixed case
		as English words,
                without normative meaning.
            </t>

        </section>
        </section>


        <section anchor="community" title="BLACKHOLE Community">
            <t>
                This document defines the use of a new well-known BGP
                transitive community, BLACKHOLE.
            </t>

            <t>
                The semantics of this community allow a network to interpret
                the presence of this community as an advisory qualification to drop
                any traffic being sent towards this prefix.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="recommendation" title="Operational Recommendations">
            <section anchor="morespecific" title="IP Prefix Announcements with BLACKHOLE Community Attached">
                <t>
                    Accepting and honoring the BLACKHOLE community,
                    or ignoring it, is a choice that is made by each
                    operator. This community MAY be used in all bilateral
                    and multilateral BGP deployment scenarios. In a bilateral
                    peering relationship, use of the BLACKHOLE community MUST
                    be agreed upon by the two networks before advertising
                    it. In a multilateral peering relationship, the decision
                    to honor or ignore the BLACKHOLE community is to be
                    made according to the operator's routing policy. The
                    community SHOULD be ignored, if it is received by a
                    network that it not using it.
                </t>
                <t>
                    When a network is under DDoS duress, it MAY announce
                    an IP prefix covering the victim's IP address(es)
                    for the purpose of signaling to neighboring networks
                    that any traffic destined for these IP address(es)
                    should be discarded. In such a scenario, the network
                    operator SHOULD attach the BLACKHOLE community.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The BLACKHOLE community MAY also be used as one of
                    the trigger communities in a destination-based Remote
		    Triggered Blackhole (RTBH) 
<xref target="RFC5635"/> configuration.
                </t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="scope" title="Local Scope of Blackholes">
                <t>
                    A BGP speaker receiving an announcement tagged
                    with the BLACKHOLE community SHOULD add the
                    NO_ADVERTISE or NO_EXPORT community as defined in
                    <xref target="RFC1997"/>, or a similar community, to
                    prevent propagation of the prefix outside the local AS.
                    The community to prevent propagation SHOULD be chosen
                    according to the operator's routing policy.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Unintentional leaking of more specific IP prefixes to
                    neighboring networks can have adverse effects. Extreme
                    caution should be used when purposefully propagating
                    IP prefixes tagged with the BLACKHOLE community
                    outside the local routing domain, unless policy
                    explicitly aims at doing just that.
                </t>
            </section>
            <section anchor="small" title="Accepting Blackholed IP Prefixes">
                <t>
                    It has been observed in provider networks running BGP
                    that announcements of IP prefixes longer than /24
                    for IPv4 and /48 for IPv6 are usually not accepted
                    on the Internet (see <xref target="RFC7454">Section
                    6.1.3 of</xref>). However, blackhole prefix length should
                    be as long as possible in order to limit the impact
                    of discarding traffic for adjacent IP space that is
                    not under DDoS duress. The blackhole prefix length is
                    typically as specific as possible, /32 for IPv4 or
                    /128 for IPv6.
                </t>
                <t>
                    BGP speakers in a bilateral peering relationship using the
                    BLACKHOLE community MUST only accept and honor BGP
                    announcements carrying the BLACKHOLE community under the
                    two following conditions:

                    <list style="symbols">
                        <t>The announced prefix is covered by an equal or
                            shorter prefix that the neighboring network is
                            authorized to advertise.</t>
                        <t>The receiving party agreed to honor the BLACKHOLE
                            community on the particular BGP session.</t>
                    </list>

                    In topologies with a route server or other multilateral
                    peering relationships, BGP speakers SHOULD accept and honor
                    BGP announcements under the same conditions.
                </t>
                <t>
                    An operator MUST ensure that origin validation techniques
                    (such as the one described in <xref target="RFC6811" />) do not inadvertently
                    block legitimate announcements carrying the BLACKHOLE
                    community.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The BLACKHOLE community is not intended to be used with
                     Network Layer Reachability
		    Information (NLRI) <xref target="RFC5575"/> to distribute traffic
                    flow specifications.
                </t>
                <t>
                    The error handling for this community follows the
                    process in <xref target="RFC7606"/> that causes a
                    malformed community to be treated as withdrawn.
                </t>
                <t>
                    Operators are encouraged to store all BGP updates in their
                    network carrying the BLACKHOLE community for long-term analysis or
                    internal audit purposes.
                </t>
            </section>
        </section>

        <section anchor="vendor" title="Vendor Implementation Recommendations">
            <t>
                Without an explicit configuration directive set by the
                operator, network elements SHOULD NOT discard traffic
                destined towards IP prefixes that are tagged with the
                BLACKHOLE community. The operator is expected to
                explicitly configure the network element to honor the
                BLACKHOLE community in a way that is compliant with the
                operator's routing policy.
            </t>
            <t>
                Vendors MAY provide a shorthand keyword in their
                configuration language to reference the well-known
                BLACKHOLE community attribute value. The suggested
                string to be used is "blackhole".
            </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
            <t>
                The IANA has registered BLACKHOLE in the "BGP Well-known Communities" registry.

                <list>
                    <t>
                        BLACKHOLE (= 0xFFFF029A)
                    </t>
                </list>
            </t>
            <t>
                The low-order two octets in decimal are 666, a value commonly
                associated with BGP blackholing among network operators.
            </t>
        </section>

        <section anchor="security" title="Security Considerations">
            <t>

                BGP contains no specific mechanism to prevent the unauthorized
                modification of information by the forwarding agent. 
   This allows routing information to be modified
   or removed; it also allows false information to
   be added by forwarding agents.  
   Recipients of
                routing information are not able to detect this modification.
                <xref target="BGPSEC">BGPsec</xref> does
                not resolve this situation. Even when BGPsec is in place, a
                forwarding agent can alter, add, or remove BGP communities.
            </t>
            <t>
                The unauthorized addition of the BLACKHOLE community to an
                IP prefix by an adversary may cause a denial-of-service attack
                based on denial of reachability.
            </t>
            <t>
                In order to further limit the impact of unauthorized BGP
                announcements carrying the BLACKHOLE community, the
                receiving BGP speaker SHOULD verify by applying strict
                filtering (see <xref target="RFC7454">Section 6.2.1.1.2 of </xref>)
                that the peer announcing the prefix is authorized to do so. If
                not, the BGP announcement should be filtered.
            </t>
            <t>
                BGP announcements carrying the BLACKHOLE community should
                only be accepted and honored if the neighboring network
                is authorized to advertise the prefix.  The method of
                validating announcements is to be chosen according to
                the operator's routing policy.
            </t>
            <t>
                It is RECOMMENDED that operators use best common practices
                to protect their BGP sessions, such as the ones in <xref
                    target="RFC7454"/>.
            </t>
        </section>

    </middle>

    <back>

        <references title="Normative References">
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1997"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4271"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7606"?>
        </references>

        <references title="Informative References">
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3882"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5575"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.5635"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6811"?>
            <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7454"?>

	    <!-- ietf-sidr-bgpsec-protocol-18 IESG state: Publication Requested -->

<reference anchor='BGPSEC'>
<front>
<title>BGPsec Protocol Specification</title>

<author initials='M' surname='Lepinski' fullname='Matthew Lepinski' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>

<author initials='K' surname='Sriram' fullname='Kotikalapudi Sriram' role="editor">
    <organization />
</author>

<date month='August' day='18' year='2016' />

</front>

<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-sidr-bgpsec-protocol-18' />
<format type='TXT'
        target='http://www.ietf.org/internet-drafts/draft-ietf-sidr-bgpsec-protocol-18.txt' />
</reference>

        </references>

        <section anchor="acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
            <t>
                The authors would like to gratefully acknowledge many people
                who have contributed discussions and ideas to the development of
                this document. They include Petr Jiran, Yordan Kritski,
                Christian Seitz, Nick Hilliard, Joel Jaeggli, Christopher
                Morrow, Thomas Mangin, Will Hargrave, Niels Bakker, David
                Farmer, Jared Mauch, John Heasley, and Terry Manderson.
            </t>
        </section>
    </back>

</rfc>
